MISSION 33 "IT'S JUST SPORTS DAY."
（任務33 是運動會）
Testing. Mic test 1-2-3.
麥克風測試，今天是晴天
When a person has extreme social anxiety,
所謂的“交流障礙症” 是指不擅長和人交流的一種症狀
they struggle to communicate with others.
或是指有這種症狀的人
Bear in mind,
不過需要注意的是
It doesn't mean that they don't want to.
但並不表示他們不想和別人有往來
I hereby declare the opening of the 23rd Itan High School Sports Day!
在此宣布伊旦高中 第23屆運動會現在開始！
Victory to our god!
將勝利獻給我們的神！
YEAAAAAH
（吶喊）
-STARTLE -KOMI'S CLASS
（驚嚇 古見同學班上的人）
It's sports day!
運動會開始囉！
Wow, you startled me!
嚇死我了！
Tadano, Komi! Sports Day is a festival!
只野同學、古見同學 運動會是歡樂慶典喔！
Let's get more hyped!
要興奮一點嘛！
You're just happy because you don't have to study.
我看你只是因為 可以不用唸書而開心吧
39.2 degrees. Hm.
39.2度，是喔
Temperature's rising, Najimi.
很熱血嘛，馴染！
Netsuno is hot-blooded.
根津野學姐非常熱血
-Wh-Who? -A NEW CHARACTER?
-她是誰啊？ -（新角色嗎？）
That's Netsuno!
是根津野學姐，妳好啊！
So you're Komi!
妳就是古見同學吧？
I'm Chika Netsuno from second year. Nice to meet you.
我是二年級的根津野千佳，請多指教
FREAKED OUT BY THE CLOSENESS.
（古見同學因對方 靠得太近而感到害怕）
Your class is 41.5 degrees. Getting pretty hot.
妳那班是41.5度，很熱血喔
Compared to that…
相較之下…
You're very cool.
妳卻非常酷
16.9 degrees. Pretty chilly.
16.9度，冷冰冰
Chilly?
冷冰冰？
I hope you won't hold your class back.
希望妳不會拖累班上的同學
What was that?
什麼跟什麼啊？
WHAP WHAP
（敲）
What's up with that woman?
那女人是有什麼毛病？
She just touched Komi. Someone's playing with fire.
摸了古見同學後轉身就走 簡直罪該萬死
Everyone! It's a fight to the death!
各位！我們要以必死的決心一戰！
YEAH!
是！
Let's just do our best.
我們正常加油就行了
Now, the rules of the sports festival.
現在說明運動會的比賽規則
It's a round-robin tournament with all classes from first to third year.
這次由一到三年級 所有班級共同進行對抗賽
Get points for your team by winning events!
在每項比賽中創下佳績就能得分！
The class with the most points wins!
獲得最高分的班級就是冠軍！
I'm your MC, Tsukasa Aizawa.
由本人會澤司擔任司儀
And our special judge is…
還有我們的特別評審…
Vice-principal here.
我是教務主任
Now, the first game is…
值得矚目的第一項比賽是…
Group Exercises!
大家一起做體操！
The person with the most beautiful form
誰的動作最優美
will earn 10 points for their class from the vice-principal!
教務主任就會送他們班十分喔！
Radio Exercise Number 1! Ready?
廣播體操第一節預備開始！
Impressive!
那是…
Netsuno from second year.
二年級的根津野同學
Big, eye-catching gestures as always!
不愧是她，大方俐落的動作 特別引人注目
There is awareness in every single fingertip.
從她每一根伸得筆直的指尖 都能看出她堅強的意志
Ah, a lovely spread.
天啊，多漂亮的開腿動作
Hmm, there are other good ones,
我看看，雖然也有其他人做得不錯
but perhaps Netsuno's the best…
但還是決定送分給根津野同學吧…
W-Wait!
這是…
BAM
（氣勢磅礴）
I changed my mind. 10 points to Komi!
不行！我要給古見同學十分！
What?
什麼？
Moving on to the second game!
好，接下來是第二項比賽！
Tug-of-War Class Tournament!
班際對抗拔河錦標賽！
Heave-ho! Heave-ho!
加油！
Heave-ho! Ko-mi! Ko-mi!
加油！古見同學！
Oh, Komi…
啊，古見同學
If you push me any harder I'm…
妳這樣用力壓著我，我不行了
-Komi's beside me… -Komi's right behind me…
-古見同學在我旁邊 -古見同學在我背後
Several people went weak, so they lost in the first round.
由於有幾個人全身無力 第一回合敗北
Obstacle Relay!
男女混合障礙接力賽！
This game also has points for artistry!
注意，這項比賽有藝術得分！
Oh… I'm slow, so I have to work hard.
不行，我這麼笨手笨腳的 我得加油才行！
For Komi!
為了古見同學！
Oh! Agari from Class 1-1!
一年一班的上理選手
Off to a slow start!
落後了大家一步！
But wait!
可是！
She got lots of points for artistry!
她獲得了大量藝術得分！
I can hear the boys sighing!
可以聽到男生們的感嘆聲！
Can Class 1-1 catch up?
一年一班能夠挽回劣勢嗎？
Why do I have to be on display like this?
為什麼我得出洋相啊？
First of all, Sports Day is a joke.
運動會這種活動本來就不該存在
Is an event that mocks the athletically-challenged
像我這種運動白痴 只會在這個學校例行活動中受辱
even needed in a hall of learning?
教育單位真的需要這種活動嗎？
No! Definitely not!
不需要！絕對不需要！
I'll just fumble through and get it over w… Oh!
算了，我隨便應付一下就好了…
What's this?
這是…
Searching for candy in a bin of starch with no hands!
要在太白粉中找到糖果的遊戲！
This is designed to make people look foolish!
玩這種遊戲一定 會成為大家的笑柄啊！
GULP
（吞口水）
Fine. I'll use my Dragon Force
好吧，只好用我的龍之力
to expertly extract a piece of candy from this sea of starch!
從這片太白粉汪洋中找出糖果來！
Now on to the next runner!
現在傳給下一棒了！
They're currently in last place! Will they be able to turn it around?
目前一年一班是最後一名 他們有機會反敗為勝嗎？
Run! Tadano!
快跑！只野！
Do it or I'll bury you!
不想被活埋的話就給我加油！
What's wrong?
怎麼了嗎？
Hey! C'mon and cheer with us!
古見同學也來跟大家一起加油吧！
Go! Go! Tadano!
加油啊！只野！
TADANO GOT DIZZY FROM SPINNING
（拿棒子原地轉圈 讓只野同學頭昏眼花）
Huh?
什麼？
You… can… do…
你要加油
it!
喔！
-They came in third. -(OUT OF 5)
-拿到了第三名 -（共五組）
52.4 degrees. You were on fire!
52.4度，你剛才很熱血喔！
Huh?
什麼？
On to the second half!
接續後半戰！
A flash rainstorm!
無預警下大雨！
It suddenly started raining.
突然就下起雨來了呢
Hopefully it stops soon.
希望雨趕快停
SPARKLE
（閃閃發光）
Komi's speaking!
古見同學在說話！
Hello. I'm Shoko's mom, Shuko.
大家好，我是硝子的母親秀子
Thanks for being so nice to Shoko!
謝謝大家和硝子做朋友！
Yeah! Shuko!
哇！秀子小姐！
Huh? What's wrong? I've come all this way to cheer for you.
幹嘛啦？虧我特地來為妳加油
They're all nice kids.
大家都是好孩子呢
Alright everyone, give it your all in the second half!
各位，後半戰也要鼓起幹勁喔！
Yeah!
好！
Class Competition Borrowing Race!
班際對抗賽借物賽跑！
-Ta-Ta-Tadano! -Hm?
-只野同學！ -什麼？
Can I borrow your jacket?
可以借你的外套嗎？
Sure!
可以啊！
Tadano.
只野同學
Lend me your hair!
借我一根頭髮！
-Huh? If I lend it, it won't come back. -I GUESS IT'S OKAY…
-什麼？可是借了就無法還了 -（要借是可以啦）
-POINTS. -My headband?
-（指） -要借頭帶嗎？
-CORRECT! -BORROW A HEADBAND.
（答對 要借的是頭帶）
Tadano!
只野同學！
Lend me a shoe, and a thousand yen.
借我一隻鞋子，另外再借我一千圓！
Nothing for you!
都不借
Schoolwide Musical Chairs!
全校學生搶椅子遊戲！
Once 100 chairs are left,
在剩下一百張椅子時
the remaining students will be awarded points for their class!
每個班級留在場中的人數 就是該班級的得分！
Here!
請坐！
Headband Stealing!
搶頭帶！
Ball Toss!
投籃遊戲！
Giant Ball Rolling!
滾大球！
And!
然後還有…
Swordfight Pole Toppling!
倒竿遊戲！
We're into the final game of the day!
運動會也接近尾聲了！
You can't miss a second!
哪怕只有一秒 也絕對不能錯過任何精彩畫面！
The final competition is!
最後一項比賽是…
Class Relay!
班際對抗接力賽跑！
Each class will choose four runners, and the first-place winner
每班派出四位代表 拿到第一名的班級竟然…
will get a hundred million points!
可以獲得一億分！
They always do that on TV variety shows!
綜藝節目裡常見的那一套！
There's a chance for every class!
每個班級都有機會喔！
I never thought we'd meet like this.
想不到會和妳在這裡對戰
Cheers.
請多指教
TREMBLE
（顫抖）
Huh?
這樣啊
MISSED OPPORTUNITY
（伸出了手對方卻收回手）
You're chilly like I thought.
妳果然是個冷冰冰的人
I don't think I'll lose.
我是不會輸給妳的
Is Komi going to be okay?
古見同學不要緊吧？
STAMPEDE
（衝上前來）
67.3 degrees!
67.3度！
Classes 1-1 and 2-3 got their batons at the same moment!
一年一班和二年三班 同時接過了棒子！
I thought you were chilly,
我以為妳這人冷冰冰的
but you really bring the heat!
想不到還挺行的嘛，古見同學！
Alright, I'll show you what I can do.
好吧，就讓妳看看我的真本事
Class 1-1 is down!
天啊，一年一班的選手摔倒了！
Komi!
古見同學！
Go, Komi!
加油，古見同學！
Looks like you're back up, Komi!
妳重新站起來了啊，古見同學！
75.6 degrees!
75.6度！
First place! 2-3!
第一位到達的是二年三班！
The winning team is Class 2-3!
冠軍是二年三班！
Sorry I said you were chilly.
抱歉之前說妳冷冰冰的
You gave 120 degrees out there!
妳讓我見識到了妳的120度！
You're blazing hot, Komi!
妳很熱血喔，古見同學！
See you next year.
明年再戰吧
Komi! Komi!
古見同學！
A-Are you okay?
妳沒事吧？
Are you injured?
有沒有受傷？
Are you alright? It doesn't hurt? We were worried!
妳還好嗎？會不會痛？ 我們都好擔心！
They're more concerned about her injuries than losing.
比起勝敗，大家更擔心她有沒有受傷
BLUBBER
（涕泗橫流）
200 degrees!
200度！
Good friends… Such good friends!
大家都是好夥伴呢！
Second place. Class 1-1. Congratulations on your valiant fight.
第二名是一年一班 在此表揚你們不屈不撓的精神
-Komi's shaking! -She must be so upset about losing!
-古見同學全身顫抖！ -她一定是很不甘心吧！
SHAKING BECAUSE EVERYONE IS LOOKING AT HER
（因為受到全校學生注目而發抖）
For a lot of people with social anxiety,
大多數有交流障礙症的人
when their friends talk to someone they don't know,
當朋友在和與自己無關的人說話時
they tend to not be able to join in.
總是無法主動加入談話
And this feeling,
而這時的感受
might be called "jealousy."
或許也可以稱為“嫉妒”吧
I feel eyes on me.
感覺背後有一道目光
Tadano, get the papers from the prep room!
只野，你去準備室拿資料過來！
Tadano, about the culture festival.
只野同學，關於文化祭的事…
Hey! When will that hidden camera for filming Komi arrive?
喂！偷拍古見同學的針孔攝影機 到底什麼時候才會送來啊？
Hey Tadano, about forming the Komi Bodyguards.
只野，古見親衛隊成立委員會的事
The ball is in your court.
就交給你了
What's the Komi Bodyguards?
“古見親衛隊”是什麼啊？
GLOOM
（憂鬱）
VICE-PRESIDENT CLASS PRESIDENT
（副班長 班長）
-Hold up! -Gurk!
-你給我站住！ -好難受！
Um, uh.
啊，妳是…
Onemine?
尾根峰同學？
-Hi! -Let me go…
-嗨 -我想出去玩啦
You're so busy with class council stuff.
只野同學，當班長很忙吧
Are you okay?
你還好嗎？
Oh. Did you want to ask me to do something?
妳也有事要來拜託我嗎？
No, no, I came to help out!
不是啦，我是來幫忙的！
W-What do you want from me?
妳有什麼目的？
You're really suffering, hey Tadano.
看來你吃過不少苦頭
-Can I take this for you? -Huh?
-這些拿過去就行了嗎？ -什麼？
Seriously, they're asking too much of you.
真是的，大家都把工作推給你
Najimi, get the papers from the prep room.
對了，馴染去準備室拿資料
There's no standing up to you, Onemine!
尾根峰，我還真是拿妳沒辦法！
-Right now! -Alright!
-動作快！ -是！
-WANTS TO HELP -Komi, will you help too?
-（也想幫忙） -古見同學也願意幫忙嗎？
Hm? The two of us can handle it.
嗯？這些量兩個人就夠了
Oh. I guess you're right.
啊，說得也是
Alright Komi. See you tomorrow.
那古見同學，明天見
Tadano, how are things?
只野同學，你最近還好嗎？
Huh? What do you mean?
怎麼了？幹嘛突然這樣問？
You know…
我是想問你…
You're being bullied, aren't you?
你被霸凌了吧？
Uh, no, I don't think so…
我覺得應該沒有吧
Really? But the teacher said…
是嗎？可是老師她…
STAFF ROOM
（教職員辦公室）
I can just make Tadano do it. Life's good!
可以把工作交給只野，真輕鬆
…as she was playing a game, so I thought…
她說這話時正在玩電玩 所以我以為你被她霸凌
Huh? Maybe I am being bullied.
這樣啊，我可能真的被霸凌了
So you were concerned and offered to help?
所以妳才來關心我，向我搭話嗎？
You guessed?
被你發現了啊？
I just can't mind my own business. Always been that way.
我這人一向就是 沒辦法對這種事置之不理
Such a good person!
她是個好人！
SCIENCE LAB
（理科教室）
Also, can I ask?
對了，我可以再問你一個問題嗎？
Sure.
請說
Are you…
只野同學…
a masochist?
你是受虐狂嗎？
Um, could you tell me how you reached that conclusion?
等等，可以告訴我 妳是怎麼得到這個結論的嗎？
After all, Komi is so beautiful and hard to approach.
因為古見同學她是個大美女 而且感覺很難接近
-Isn't it a lot of pressure? -Huh?
-她盛氣凌人，對吧？ -什麼？
Is it?
會嗎？
So for someone like you, an avera…
所以像你這麼平凡…
a normal guy like you to always be with her…
這樣的普通人卻常和她在一起 我才會猜想…
I guess you must be into pain.
你是不是喜歡被人瞪啊？
Oh, don't worry. I totally get it!
你放心，我不會介意這種事的！
It's not like that at all.
妳誤會了啦
I don't feel any pressure being with Komi.
而且古見同學一點都不會盛氣凌人喔
You'll understand if you talk to her. I think she'd like that.
妳只要跟她聊過就會明白 她應該會很開心
Really?
真的嗎？
But everyone puts her on such a pedestal.
可是大家老是在奉承她
She must look down on…
她應該是高高在上的那種人…
She really doesn't.
沒這回事
Huh.
是喔
Anyway, if you're ever having trouble, you can talk to me.
總之有什麼煩惱 歡迎找大姐姐我商量
Thank you!
謝謝妳！
Huh? Komi? What's wrong?
什麼？古見同學怎麼了？
STARE
（凝視）
You'll understand if you talk to her. I think she'd like that.
妳只要跟她聊過就會明白 她應該會很開心
H-Hi there, Komi…
嗨，古見同學…
-Huh? -Oh!
-什麼？ -啊！
Um, oh, that's just, uh.
不是啦，妳不要誤會
How can I explain? Hmm.
該怎麼說呢？好難說明
-AFTER SCHOOL. -Bye! See ya!
-（放學後） -拜拜，明天見！
GLOOM
（憂鬱）
They gave you work again?
大家又把工作推給你了嗎？
I guess I'll help you.
真拿你沒辦法，我來幫忙吧
Oh, uh, no. That's…
啊，不用啦…
If you say no, I'll just make more work for you!
你要是拒絕 我也會讓你的工作量增加喔！
Such a good person!
她是個大好人！
-Komi, you can go on home. -IT'D BE BAD TO MAKE HER WAIT…
-古見同學，妳可以先回去了 -（也不好意思讓妳等）
One, two, three, four, five, six, ten.
一、二、三、四、五、六、十
Let's make quick work of this.
好，我們就快完成工作吧
Alright!
好！
This is for the culture festival…
這是文化祭用的…
And this is for the teacher.
還有這個是班導的吧
Got it.
瞭解
I WANT TO HELP, TOO.
（我也想要幫忙）
Ah, alright. Please do. It'll help a lot.
不好意思，那就麻煩妳了 真是幫了大忙
Why are you so eager to help?
妳為什麼那麼想幫忙啊？
Ah, so for this document here,
那就先看這一段文章
I want to tally up A, B, and C, so if you can circle this…
我想合計A、B、C 如果妳可以幫忙圈出這個…
Sorry!
對不起！
I had plans today.
我忘了我今天還有事
I gotta go! Really sorry!
我先回去了，真的很抱歉！
Bye, you two.
兩位再見啦
Huh?
嗯？
THE NEXT DAY
（隔天）
Hey you two!
嗨，兩位早安啊！
Was that a little too buddy-buddy?
我這樣算是在裝熟嗎？
SORRY ABOUT YESTERDAY. YOU SPOKE TO ME BUT I RAN AWAY.
（昨天妳找我說話，我卻逃跑 真的很抱歉）
GOOD MORNING.
（早安）
Sorry, that just tickled me.
抱歉，戳中我笑點了
Ah, Komi.
啊，古見同學
Sorry I was hanging out with Tadano yesterday.
抱歉，我昨天不該纏著只野同學
I'm rooting for the two of you.
我支持你們兩個喔
Uh, Komi?
等等，古見同學？
What did you say to her?
妳跟她說了什麼呀？
Huh?
嗯？
That's between me and Komi.
那是我和古見同學之間的祕密
DID YOU SEE IT?
（各位有發現嗎？）
IT SEEMS THAT PHOTO STICKERS ARE POPULAR THESE DAYS.
（聽說最近流行一種 叫大頭貼的東西）
Yes, I guess so.
好像是吧
-I WAS THINKING IT SEEMS FUN… -Yeah.
-（我覺得非常有意思…） -這樣啊
Do you want to go?
所以妳是想拍拍看嗎？
I heard that!
我聽到了喔！
You?
你是…
Have no fear, Photogenic Najimi is here!
超級上相的馴染登場了！
Huh? What? Say that again.
什麼？說了什麼？再說一遍
We can go to the arcade by the station.
我們可以去車站前的電玩中心
What? You're going to take photo stickers?
什麼？你們要去拍大頭貼嗎？
Without me?
居然沒邀我？
It's…
妳是…
Filter Queen Yamai!
超愛開美顏濾鏡的山井！
What's this bit you're doing?
你從剛才就在說些什麼啊？
It's been ages.
好久沒來了
I used to take a lot in junior high.
國中時倒是常來拍
Yeah.
就是啊
Komi?
古見同學？
SPARKLE
（閃閃發光）
There are a lot of different types.
有好多種類喔
Hey! We're starting!
喂，要拍囉！
Choose a frame.
請選擇你喜歡的相框
Is this one okay?
這個可以嗎？
Which filter will you use?
請問要用哪種濾鏡？
Beautiful skin mode.
清爽美肌模式
Komi, you already have nice skin, so you'd just disappear.
古見同學皮膚本來就很好 開這個濾鏡會把妳變不見吧
Big clear eyes mode.
炯炯有神大眼模式
Komi already has big eyes, so you'd just look like an alien.
古見同學眼睛本來就很大 開這個濾鏡會變成外星人吧
Full-body long-legged model mode.
全身長腿模特兒模式
Komi already has long legs, so you'd just look weird.
古見同學腿本來就很長 開這個濾鏡腳會過長，會很奇怪吧
Huh?
什麼？
There's no filter we can use for Komi!
沒有古見同學可以用的模式！
First, a cute one. Smile big!
先拍一張可愛的，笑一個！
-Now make a cute angry pose. -EMBARRASSED
-接著擺出生氣的姿勢 -（難為情）
Last, do some funny faces together!
最後感情融洽地扮鬼臉！
FRIENDS FOREVER!
（永遠都是朋友！）
-They're awful! Ha ha ha! -IS IT OKAY TO LAUGH?
-這太扯了，哈哈哈！ -（可以笑嗎？）
Adorable!
太可愛了！
I laughed so hard I'm hungry now.
一直大笑，肚子都餓了
Let's get a snack!
我們去吃點東西吧！
Yeah.
好啊
THANKS EVERYONE.
（謝謝大家）
Komi?
古見同學？
Good morning, Komi.
早安，古見同學
GOOD MORNING.
（早安）
Hang on.
對了
Here.
這給妳
When we went to the arcade,
上次我們大家一起去電玩中心時
you were looking at it.
妳一直在看著這個
I figured maybe you wanted one.
我猜妳應該是很想要
I just happened to get it on the first try.
沒有啦，我碰巧一次就夾到了！
It's not like… It's okay if you don't want it.
如果妳不要也沒關係
WAVE WAVE
（搖手）
AFTER THAT, I GOT NAJIMI TO TAKE ME.
（後來我硬要馴染再帶我去一次）
Oh, is that what happened?
啊，原來是這樣啊？
Then I guess you don't need…
那妳就不需要這個了…
Komi?
古見同學？
LET'S TRADE.
（我們交換吧）
Here.
好
Morning!
早安啊！
Huh? What's up?
嗯？怎麼了呀？
Hey! What's going on?
你們怎麼了？
Hey! Hey!
說啊！
TOO EMBARRASSED TO PUT THEM ON THEIR BAGS
（因為太難為情 兩人都不敢掛在書包外面）
Shoko, dinner…
硝子，吃晚飯了…
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻譯：馬慈光